A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 5, Accession 5 FA1187
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 5, Accession 5
1950-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations
FA1187
25.64 Cubic Feet 63 document boxes, 1 oversized flat box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist. When requesting audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China. The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach. Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received little or no physical rearrangement. RG 5 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into nine series: 2 – Exchanges - General; 3 – Exchanges to China; 4 – Exchanges from China; 5 – Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues; 6 – Publications and Reports; 8 – Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 10 – Development; 11 – Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records; and 15 – Clippings and Reference.
Scope and Contents
RG 5 documents several of the NCUSCR's early projects and outreach programs in the late 1960s and early 1970s, including Curriculum Development and audiovisual projects, a China Trade Study, seminars for Young Business Leaders and other professionals, and its first National Convocation on the U. S. and China. Exchange materials include a collection of trip reports from early National Committee delegates to China as well as reports from other, non-affiliated exchange delegations. Later programs documented in RG 5 include the Ussuri Project collaboration in the 1990s, the Time Warner Internship Program, 1998-2006, and the visit of the China Fund for the Handicapped delegation in 1987.
RG 5 notably includes the full run of National Committee Board Minutes and Materials from 1966 to 2007. Other material of interest includes Foundation Correspondence - often grant related - in the Development series.
- Exchanges - General, 1976-1981; 2
  - Memos on the Exchange Process, 1976 (Box 33, Folder 334)
  - Briefings by National Committee Staff, 1976-1981 (Box 33, Folder 335)
    Scope and Contents
    General file on briefings given to various exchange groups.
- Exchanges to China, 1972-1981; 3
  The Exchanges to China series in RG 5 contains collected trip reports from the first National Committee delegation trip to China in 1972-1973, and from academic and civic leaders who participated in the University Presidents and World Affairs delegations in 1974 and 1975. Reports by individuals who traveled to China from 1973-1981, under the aegis of other organizations, complete the series.
  - First National Committee Delegation: Reports (A. Doak Barnett), 1972 December 11 - 1973 January 6 (Box 33, Folder 336)
    "China Revisited: A Country in Transition".
  - First National Committee Delegation: Reports (Alexander Eckstein, China Trip Notes), 1972 December 11 - 1973 January 6 (Box 33, Folder 337)
  - First National Committee Delegation: Reports (John Wilson Lewis, China Trip Notes), 1972 December 11 - 1973 January 6 (Box 33, Folder 338-340)
  - First National Committee Delegation: Reports (Robert Scalapino, China Trip, 1972 December 11 - 1973 January 6 (Box 33, Folder 341-342)
  - University and College Presidents Delegation: Reports (William G. Bowen), 1974 November 8-29 (Box 33, Folder 343)
    Informal diary, WGB Notes on China (full and partial versions), "University Education in the People's Republic of China: A Visitor's Impressions."
  - University and College Presidents Delegation: Delegation and Other Reports, 1974 November 8-29 (Box 34, Folder 344-345)
    Delegation report and individual reports by Harold L. Enarson, Robben W. Fleming, Merle Goldman, Richard W. Lyman, Martha Peterson, Nathan W. Pusey, John D. Rockefeller IV, Granville M. Sawyer, and Howard R. Swearer.
  - World Affairs Delegation: Reports (Harlan Cleveland, China Diary), 1975 October 6-23 (Box 34, Folder 346-347)
    Manuscript and published report. File also includes 1977 commentary by Eleanor B. Morris.
  - World Affairs Delegation: Reports (Robert G. Chollar), 1975 October 6-23 (Box 34, Folder 348)
    "The China Model: Some Observations on Its Vulnerability to Technological Change." Two versions.
  - World Affairs Delegation: Reports (John Knowles, China Diary), 1975 October 6-23 (Box 34, Folder 349)
  - World Affairs Delegation: Reports (Allen S. Whiting), 1975 October 6-23 (Box 34, Folder 350)
    Delegation report.
  - World Affairs Delegation: Other Reports, 1975 October 6-23 (Box 34, Folder 351)
    Reports by Carter L. Burgess, Richard G. Heggie, James F. Leonard, Jean Picker, John E. Rielly, and Carol Baumann.
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: General, 1973-1976, 1980 (Box 35, Folder 352)
    Scott and Helen Nearing, et al., 1973, Jermaine Magnuson's China Diary, 1973, Julia and Leon Winston, 1975, Mary de G. White, 1976, William B. Smart, UPI, 1978, American Council of Learned Societies - SSRC, 1980.
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: First American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE) Delegation, 1972 September 29 - October 22 (Box 35, Folder 353)
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (CSCPRC) Visit, 1973 May 15 - June 15 (Box 35, Folder 354)
    Scott and Helen Nearing, et al., 1973, Jermaine Magnuson's China Diary, 1973, Julia and Leon Winston, 1975, Mary de G. White, 1976.
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: University of Arizona Delegation, 1976 June 15 - July 2 (Box 35, Folder 355)
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: Mathematics Education Study Visit (National Council of Teachers of Mathematics), 1977 October-November (Box 35, Folder 356-357)
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: Stanford International Security and Arms Control Group Visit, 1978 July 10-19 (Box 35, Folder 358)
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: Chinese - English Translation Assistance (CETA) Delegation, 1979 April (Box 35, Folder 359)
    Computers, Language Reform, and Lexicography in China: A Report by the CETA Delegation.
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: Health Care Study Tour (University of Michigan - Dearborn and Michigan State University), 1979 August 2-19 (Box 35, Folder 360-361)
    Group Journal, "Health Care and the People's Republic of China", Marilynn M. Rosenthal, "Political Process and the Integration of Traditional and Western Medicine in the People's Republic of China."
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) Visit, 1979 November 1-17 (Box 35, Folder 362)
  - Non - NCUSCR Trip Reports: California State University, Northridge, Mission to China, 1981 April 3-24 (Box 35, Folder 363)
- Exchanges from China, 1977-1988; 4
  The Exchanges from China series in RG 5 documents the visit in October 1987 of the China Fund for the Handicapped delegation, headed by Deng Pufang (son of Deng Xiaoping), who was disabled after a fall from a window during the Cultural Revolution. Deng originally planned to visit in 1986, but he had to cancel his trip for health reasons. While it was a National Committee member who first broached the idea of a visit, other organizations – some with their own agendas – took interest in the project, which complicated the planning and created some conflicts.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): General, 1987 October 1-22 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    Namelists, Guidelines, Itineraries. Includes chronology and background information on Deng Pufang visit.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 9, Folder 84-87)
    Includes folders labeled "Correspondence with China" and "Correspondence with China Welfare Fund" (mainly concerning planning for Deng Pufang's proposed trip in 1986).
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Jan Berris Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Background and Planning (1986 Visit) (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Background and Planning, 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 90-91)
    Materials date from 1984-1987. Includes correspondence on Hotels and Travel.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Public Interest in Visit, 1984-1987 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    Original folder entitled People and Institutions Wishing Involvement in Visit.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visit Planning (1986 Visit) (Box 10, Folder 93)
    Indianapolis, Chicago, Minneapolis, San Francisco
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Draft Invitation Lists, 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visits (New York), 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    Includes planning for 1986 trip.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visits (Washington D.C.), 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visits (Maryland), 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visits (Florida), 1987 October 1-22 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Visits (Los Angeles and San Francisco), 1987 October 1-22 (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Publicity and Press Coverage, 1987 October 1-22 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - FA1187:005 - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Publicity and Press Coverage, 1987 October 1-22; Still Image: 30 color 3x5 prints. (Box 63, Folder 100)
    30 images taken on two (?) occasions of Deng with unidentified hosts at a reception (3 images) and exchanging gifts (27 images).
  - FA1187:006 - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Publicity and Press Coverage, 1987 October 1-22; Still Image: 3 Black and white glossy prints (5x7 and 8x10) (Box 63, Folder 100)
    Informal portrait of Deng, Deng with former Prime Minister Edward Heath, photo of postage stamps in series "Chinese Handicapped Persons."
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Thank Yous and Follow-Up, 1987 October 1-22 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Supplementary Material, 1980-1988 (Box 11, Folder 102-106)
    Includes materials on Rehabilitation International, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Project on the Handicapped in Science,.
  - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Supplementary Material, 1977-1987 (Box 12, Folder 107-111)
    Includes material on National Theatre of the Deaf and Center for Therapeutic Riding, Washington, DC, Suffolk County, NY, BOCES and Cerebral Palsy Association, Kaiser Roll Foundation, World Institute on Disability and Center for Independent Living, Berkeley, CA.
  - FA1187:017 - China Fund for the Handicapped Delegation (Deng Pufang): Supplementary Material, 1984-1985; Oversized: Brochure 11.5 x 11.5" (Box 64, Folder 107)
    Brochure on the National Theatre of the Deaf, 1984-1985.
- Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues, 1967-1976; 5
  The Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues series in RG 5 documents some of the National Committee's early public outreach programs, such as its seminars and briefings, 1967-1969, for Young Business Executives and Aerospace and Electronics Executives, and, especially, its First National Convocation, held in New York in March 1969. Viewed as an opportunity for fundraising as well as public educational outreach, the First National Convocation occasioned considerable press coverage, and an edited volume of papers, The United States and China: The Next Decade, was published in 1970. Finally, this series also includes proposals for follow-up symposia and records for "cooperative" (or jointly sponsored) symposia in 1971-1973, such as the Fund for Peace Convocation and a conference on China's Developmental Experience.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: General, 1969 March 20-21 (Box 22, Folder 216)
    First National Convocation, The United States and China: The Next Decade. Program brochure and announcements.
  - FA1187:011 - Convocation on the U. S. and China: General, 1969 March 20-21; Still Images: 38 black and white 4.75 x 7" glossy prints, plus 3 cropped and mounted prints (3.25 x 7 - 5.5 x 7) (Box 63, Folder 216)
    Professional photographs of speakers and participants. Includes a few duplicate prints.
  - FA1187:012 - Convocation on the U. S. and China: General, 1969 March 20-21; Still Image: Black and white 8 x 10 glossy print (2 copies) (Box 63, Folder 216)
    Panel of speakers at the Convocation.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Harold L. Oram Inc., 1968-1969 (Box 22, Folder 217)
    Fundraising and program planning. Harold Oram was a fundraising and public relations specialist.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Program Development, 1968-1969 (Box 22, Folder 218)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Budget, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 219)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Conference Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 22, Folder 220)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Letters of Appreciation and General Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 22, Folder 221)
    File includes follow-up comments on the Convocation, which seem to have been added to an earlier file of correspondence on the National Committee and its 1967-1968 programs. Original folder labeled "Comments - Nice Letters".
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: General Correspondence, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 222)
    Individuals and Organizations and Embassies
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Corporation Correspondence (A-C), 1969 (Box 22, Folder 223)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Corporation Correspondence (D-L), 1969 (Box 22, Folder 224)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Corporation Correspondence (N-Z), 1969 (Box 23, Folder 225)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Corporation Invitations (Telegrams), 1969 March 20-21 (Box 23, Folder 226)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Speakers Correspondence (A-I), 1969 (Box 23, Folder 227)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Speakers Correspondence (J-M), 1969 (Box 23, Folder 228)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Speakers Correspondence (N-Z)), 1969 (Box 23, Folder 229)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Mailing to Organizations, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 230)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Requests for Tickets and Brochures, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 231)
    Requests for conference tickets, especially for students. Original folder labeled, "Oram Mailing I Current II." Note on folder indicates that correspondence should be used "for resource list".
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Volunteers and Outside Staff, 1969 March 20-21 (Box 23, Folder 232)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Press Invitations and Attendance, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 233)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Sponsors, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 234)
    Corporations, Foundations, and Individuals.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Dinners and Luncheons, 1969 March 19-21 (Box 24, Folder 235)
    Dinner honoring John Keswick, hosted by Najeeb Halaby, March 19, Reception at the United Nations, March 20, Dinner featuring Senator Edward M. Kennedy as speaker, March 20, Luncheons, March 20 and 21. Materials mainly concern dais invitations and guest attendance.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: New York Hilton, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 236)
  - FA1187:020 - Convocation on the U. S. and China: New York Hilton, 1969; Oversized: 3 plans (approx. 25.5" x 29"). File in Map Case. (Box 64, Folder 236)
    Seating Plans for Grand Ballroom and East Ballroom. Grand Ballroom plan marked on back, Dinner Council on U. S. and China. East Ballroom plan includes names of organizations taking tables.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Speeches (Advance Texts), 1969 March 20-21 (Box 24, Folder 237)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Publication (General), 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 238)
    NCUSCR staff Martha Goell and Elinor Bacon correspondence concerning publication and editing of volume, reviews of The United States and China: The Next Decade, 1970.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Publication (Correspondence with Contributors), 1969 (Box 24, Folder 239)
    Correspondence concerning editing of "The United States and China: The Next Decade" manuscript.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Publication (Correspondence with Editors), 1969 (Box 24, Folder 240)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Publication (Mervyn Adams), 1969-1970 (Box 25, Folder 241)
    Adams was the editor at Praeger for The United States and China: The Next Decade.
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Edited Remarks, 1969 (Box 25, Folder 242-245)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Book Manuscript, 1969 (Box 25, Folder 246-247)
    Copy of edited manuscript of [The United States and China: The Next Decade].
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Press Coverage, 1969 (Box 26, Folder 248-265)
    Files sorted by categories, subjects, and sources. The majority of materials focus on Senator Edward M. Kennedy's address.
  - Convocation on China and Southeast Asia (Proposal), 1970 (Box 26, Folder 266)
  - Symposium Proposal, 1969-1970 (Box 26, Folder 267)
    Proposal for a national symposium on the origins of American attitudes to China to be held in the spring of 1970 as a follow-up to the NCUSCR's Dialogue on China and Convocation.
  - Munthe-Kaas, Harald, 1968 (Box 36, Folder 364)
    General file on Harald Munthe-Kaas's seminar and lecture tour.
  - FA1187:013 - Munthe-Kaas, Harald, 1968; Still Images: 3 black and white prints (3.5" x 4"), mounted on a sheet of paper. (Box 63, Folder 364)
    Harald Munthe-Kaas at World Affairs Council Luncheon, Dallas, TX, 1968 January 15. Includes images with Gen. John D. Torrey Jr., Ed Gossett, and Lee Drain.
  - Young Business Executives Briefing: Edwin O. Reischauer, 1969 March 11 (Box 36, Folder 365)
  - Young Business Executives Briefing: William Bundy, 1969 June 4 (Box 36, Folder 366)
  - Young Business Executives Briefing: Herman Kahn, 1969 October 21 (Box 36, Folder 367)
  - Young Business Executives Briefing: Harrison Salisbury, 1969 December 16 (Box 36, Folder 368)
  - Young Business Executives Briefing: Fundraising, 1969 (Box 36, Folder 369)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Transcripts (March 20), 1969 March 20-21 (Box 36, Folder 370-371)
  - Convocation on the U. S. and China: Transcripts (March 21), 1969 March 20-21 (Box 36, Folder 372-373)
  - Members Symposium: Correspondence and Planning, 1971 June 3-4 (Box 36, Folder 374-375)
    Symposium held in Washington, DC.
  - Members Symposium: Invitations and Responses, 1971 June 3-4 (Box 37, Folder 376)
    Invitations to Members and Non-Members.
  - Members Symposium: Local Arrangements, 1971 June 3-4 (Box 37, Folder 377)
  - China's Developmental Experience: Background and Planning, 1971-1972, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 378-379)
  - China's Developmental Experience: Correspondence with Participants, 1972-1973 (Box 37, Folder 380-381)
  - China's Developmental Experience: Papers, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 382-383)
    Michel Oksenberg, ed.
  - Fund for Peace Convocation: Program Development, 1971 October 29 (Box 38, Folder 384-385)
    Fund for Peace, Third National Convocation on "The Challenge of Building Peace: The United States and China." Original folder description: Record of Program Development, Purposes, Speaker suggestions.
  - Fund for Peace Convocation: General Correspondence, 1971 October 29 (Box 38, Folder 386)
  - Fund for Peace Convocation: Correspondence (A-Z), 1971 October 29 (Box 38, Folder 387-391)
    Correspondence with invitees and participants.
  - Fund for Peace Convocation: Press Information, 1971 October 29 (Box 38, Folder 392)
  - Perceptions Seminar Planning, 1967, 1969-1971 (Box 45, Folder 445)
  - Seminars for Aerospace Executives, 1967 October 11 - December 13 (Box 45, Folder 446)
    A series of three luncheon seminars at MIT, organized by the National Committee and its Harvard Field Staff.
  - Seminars for California Aerospace and Electronics Executives, 1968 November 6 - 1969 January 27 (Box 45, Folder 447)
  - Seminars for California Aerospace and Electronics Executives (Cancelled), 1969 May 21 (Box 45, Folder 448)
  - Seminars for California Aerospace and Electronics Executives (Speaker Correspondence), 1968-1969 (Box 45, Folder 449)
  - Seminar on China for Western Journalists (Proposed), 1969 May (Box 45, Folder 450)
  - University Outreach Programs on East Asia: Linkages with School and Community, 1975-1976 (Box 53, Folder 513-514)
    Correspondence and Report on Wingspread Conference, September 28-29, 1975. See also FA1186, RG 4, box 60, folders 580-584. File originally labeled "U. S. Office of Education" (the International Studies Branch helped to underwrite conference costs).
- Publications and Reports, 1965-1975; 6